Greetings. My name is Dr. Christopher Andrews, and in this video we're going to be talking about engineering lab reports and technical writing.
The Accreditation Board for Engineering Technology
(or ABET) says that one of the important student learning outcomes for
engineering programs is that those students
need to be able to communicate effectively
with a range of different audiences.
This workshop is intended to help you
think about writing a little bit differently than
you may have before:
in particular thinking about writing as a
professional who communicates with audiences.
And to help you recognize
strategies that are going to
improve the writing that you're doing
to make it more effective for readers
and have that reader orientation.
ABET says when you graduate from this program
you should have an ability to
communicate effectively with a range of audiences.
If this were a face-to-face workshop,
I'd invite you to do a writing activity
and we'd have a short discussion.
But I'll just let you think about these questions
for a minute or two on your own.
Why does effective communication matter?
When or why do you think engineers use writing?
Effective communication is how work happens.
It comes before work,
supports work during the process,
and sustains work after a project is completed.
Mechanical engineers utilize writing daily
to propose projects and justify design ideas,
to create manufacturing instructions,
record and report test results,
or verify progress on a project.
They also disseminate information to help people make decisions and even persuade or recommend based on their expert opinion.
In fact, that's one of the reasons
why your accreditation matters--it's because
your expert opinion has to stand for something.
The audiences that these documents communicate to are varied.
Engineers must be able to effectively communicate complex topics and ideas to other engineers, technical and non-technical personnel,
business personnel, marketing professionals, and the public.
Frankly, engineers.... they write a lot!
These details are just a brief survey of some of the literature about how much time you're going to spend writing.
Obviously, the first few years on the job, comparatively maybe not too much;
but as you continue up the ladder of your career
you're going to write more and more. This might be something as simple as the ever-present email,
but obviously all the way up to reports, recommendations,
and those sorts of things as well.
Rather than thinking of writing as
a hoop that you have to jump through or
some awful thing that you have to do when really the more important work is the actual engineering of things,
writing is a part of your tool collection.
So instead of thinking of yourself as just writing something, consider that you're using writing or using a tool to do something.
When we think about writing is using tools to do, such as
explaining a complex system in such a way that others can understand it,
we're really inviting a couple of questions:
What are we really doing with a lab report or a project proposal or a progress report or whatever it is?
That is, how are other people going to use what we produce?
Then how does that affect our choices and uses of the tools that we use to produce that piece of writing?
We're making choices about tools based on what it's going to end up being or doing in the end.
Briefly, before we get into some of the
strategies for technical writing,
I'd like to talk about writing for grades
versus writing in the workplace.
Writing for grades is really all about achieving.college goals:
showing your professor that you did to work correctly, that you mastered a subject matter,
that you would like to get a good grade. And really its oriented to one single reader: the professor.
This is the kind of writing that you're most familiar with,
that you've spent a lot of time doing and
learning how to do: these essays of papers that you've done throughout your college career, and even before then in high school.
But we think about writing in the workplace, it's not about pleasing the professor and jumping through hoops to get a good grade.
It's really about communicating information to audiences who need to use it.
Like I was listing before: people who need to make a decision or who need to be able to follow a process or
because we need to document that something happened,
or explain how something was done, or even justify what you did and why you did it for other professionals.
And this means that there are a variety of different readers:
Professionals, people who have your similar expertise or people who have very little of your own expertise and a variety of stakeholders
including users,
businesspeople,
and a variety of other audiences. Writing in the workplace is complex
bt it's also very very functionally oriented.
Well, let's get into some of the bits and pieces about technical writing.
Technical writing uses simple direct language and document design features to convey information to audiences.
This presentation is going to oversimplify some of these concepts, but hopefully those are useful oversimplifications.
And I'll offer a few examples of each principle in action;
these examples aren't perfect,
but they highlight some areas that you might be struggling with as a writer.
And really, all of these five principles
emphasize the idea of being direct about what happened, why it happened, and why it matters.
The examples that we'll look out are really oriented around these five points:
First and most important point: write to your audience. What do they need? What do they know?
What do they not know? You need to tell them what they need to know.
You need to make sure that you are not assuming things that they know or telling them things that they don't need to know.
Ultimately that results in "getting to the point."
Technical writing is not mystery writing; it's not a mystery or suspense novel.
We're really getting directly to the point because people want to make a decision and move on with their lives.
Number three: put information where your readers expect it to be. What do readers want?
What do readers expect?
That's really how they're going to judge things.
In fact,
if a lot of the formal pieces are there, sometimes readers can be pretty forgiving on some of the smaller
stylistic issues. (In some cases.)
Number four: We need to label everything.
Because writing in engineering relies so much on visuals
it's important to provide context and information about visuals,
to help readers find and locate what exactly they're looking for, to label sections appropriately, figures and tables and equations
so that somebody who's scanning through the document quickly can very easily find the information that they're looking for.
Finally, number five you need to explain visuals or data before you show them.
This can actually be hard because we often think that the data are self-explanatory.
Obviously, you know here if we did the thing and there are the numbers and aren't the numbers self-explanatory?
Well, they are to you because you were there and you did the experiment; but to somebody who wasn't there or somebody who doesn't have
the same level of technical knowledge about what you're doing--which many of your readers might not have,
you need to do a little bit of explanation about what the visuals are trying to show,
what you're trying to emphasize, what the most important data points are, etcetera.
And you do that before you show data. This can be a common trip-up area for beginning technical writers.
So again, the first thing is to write to your audience.
What are you doing with a lab report? What the different parts of a report do?
How's that analogous to or similar to communicating that you might do on the job? Who's going to use it? For what purposes?
A ab report is a detailed account of an experiment, its methods, its results, and its conclusions all of which answer
some question: some design question or some problem.
When you're thinking about your lab report you need to answer: What is the question
that your lab report is answering? What is the problem that it's trying to solve? That is, the experiment itself.
Possible audiences for lab reports: you can think about this is something directed towards engineers or peers who are interested in similar work and might
base their experiment on yours.
You might think about another audience being a supervisor who wants to know about the work that you have done.
Obviously your professor or grader is also part of the audience and
their job as a marker is to dramatize the presence of these other two audiences: people who aren't inside your brain and
don't know exactly what you know. Thus, it's your job to explain to them what you're doing and why.
Some important purposes for a lab report:
Obviously you need to inform. People want to know what you have done.
There's also a little bit of persuasion
--or we might better say "justification"--
going on in the lab report as well.
Raw data is not convincing by itself.
You have to convince your audience that it's correct,
and you need to justify your results.
That is, you want them to understand that this is valid data that you got it in a particular way
through a particular process that they are able to see and perhaps validate on their own.
On this slide
we're going to spend a little bit of time talking about what the major sections of a lab report is going to do.
What information do they provide for different kinds of audiences?
The abstract can be tricky,
but the abstract is a summary
of what you did and what you concluded.
The core results and essentials to help other people understand what you did and why.
The abstract is very brief; think of it as one sentence for each major section of your report, more or less.
This is the top-level summary that you might drop in an email and send to the supervisor so they can know okay
What happened? What did you do about it? Okay, and they're moving on with their life. That's what an abstract does.
The introduction is
much less specific than the abstract
The introduction really explains and develops the problem that you're trying to solve, the question that you're trying to answer
so that people understand "why the heck we're doing this in the first place."
It also explains why the problem needs solving, offering some sort of rationale for why this is worth doing.
The next major section is the theory or sometimes called the background section. This is where as an engineer
you're explaining your assumptions about how things should work, or how according to
theory things are supposed to happen.
If there's major terminology or equations, this is also where you'll describe these technical concepts and explain why the
equation was used in this particular way in this particular situation.
In the theory you talk about what you expect to happen or why you expect the problem to be solved in this particular way.
The equipment and procedure sections, sometimes called a method section, in some sorts of lab reporting,
is really about describing and illustrating the equipment and the steps of what you did and how you did it.
This is ultimately framed so that someone could replicate and ultimately verify your process.
In the data,
calculations, or results sections, you're going to present and explain what you found using graphs or tables with short explanations to point out
key data points,
most important calculations, most important results. This will be a fairly short data heavy section.
But that's very important as you move into the discussion and analysis sections.
In these sections you explain your results,
comparing them with what you expected or
other calculated results.
This might be a section where you return
back to some of those theory ideas and
explain why this happened or why this worked out according to theory.
Finally in the conclusion section, that's where you're interpreting and judging the results. Restate the problem.
Restate the results. Justify the decisions that you made or justify what happened.
This is also an appropriate place to explain abnormality,
errors, or uncertainties,
as well as to discuss problems and how those might be corrected in the future. All of these different parts work together and work in
very specific ways so that readers can get to exactly the information that they need at exactly the time or place that they need it.
Some people are just going to need the procedure,
they need to know how to make that part that you made and
so they're just going to read the procedure section so they can understand here's the steps that they need to go through.
Meanwhile, another engineer
might be more interested in the
potential anomalies or problems and how they might deal with those in the future. So they're gonna jump straight to your conclusions
so they can understand, "Well, here's what happened. And here's how it broke
And here's what I need to do to fix it in the future."
Let's dig into some of these
sections and some of these problems
in more particular detail.
One of those principles was "get to the point" and so we'll look at an example of an abstract
that doesn't quite do the job, as well as an example of an abstract that does a little bit of a better job.
Again, what's an abstract's purpose? Who is it for? What do readers expect about the abstract?
The abstract only sets out the problem; it
summarizes the contents of the report very very briefly.
This abstract has a couple of problems.
If you look with me at the first sentence:
"This lab report will break down into details the procedure taken to develop the plate and shaft two-part assembly."
"Explanations and figures will aid in the rendition of the report."
Well, those both are true, but they're not really telling us anything about the experiment itself.
You'll also see further down where we get into the sentence
"The purpose of this experiment was to create a two-part aluminum plate and shaft, etc, etc."
This is really where the business of the abstract really gets down to, down here.
Summarizing the experiment and moving on to the contents of the report.
This abstract does a little bit of a better job. It begins right on front street:
"The objective of the lab was to build an assembly that was able to withstand a
ten foot-pound torque applied at the end of the shaft without turning." That's the problem that's trying to be solved.
Then it delves into some
concerns about materials and
important steps in the process. )ne thing that might improve
this abstract is a little bit more precision about results: a few pieces of data about contact pressure, for example, would be acceptable.
But it does overview the scope of the project and is providing about a sentence worth of summary for each major section of the report.
We have a few sentences about the objective of the lab,
a few sentences about the overall process
of how the lab was accomplished, and then we do have a little bit of conclusion or results.
Here's what happened: "in optimal conditions
contact pressure wouldn't exceed the yield strength of the material we used and it sustained too much contact pressure"
So, further things might be done." Again, it's just a snapshot of each step in the process.
The next two slides look at a couple of examples of introductions.
introductions
This first introduction explains some of the learning objectives of the lab,
but it doesn't really introduce the essential problem that needed to be solved in the lab.
The lab report should be focused on those engineering problems:
what was the experiment and why does it need to be done in an engineering context?
In this case telling us about becoming familiar with machining tolerances,
gaining a better understanding for material performance, and developing a respect for the art of machining are all good, but essentially those are "fluff".
Really this needs to be about what was this experiment trying to solve. What was the engineering problem this was trying to solve?
The other problem with this
Introduction is that it launches into
specifications and details
about the process and results.
both of these--
the description of specific tolerances that we're machining the the shaft to, and then
the particular results of the process--both of these belong a little bit in the abstract and even more so in the
overview of theory and results sections.
This introduction begins with the experiment: creating an assembly meeting given specifications,
test the capability of the interference fit used to secure two pieces together. And then it goes on to explain
why the audience should care about it and describes the implications of the process.
"Interference fits, or press fits, are common means of combining independent parts."
And "This is important for creating the product;
discovering it's defective through experimentation is cheaper and
less destructive than discovering that it doesn't work out in the field."
Obviously, this gets right to the
essential issues from an engineering context, and that's very important for the introduction.
The next principle here looks at some procedures.
And again, we think about, if you're going to follow a procedure, follow a manual, what do you expect that to look like?
This is a narrative version of a procedure and it's really not quite as strong as the next version.
We can see "once both parts were finished",
"finally the shaft was placed back on to the mill and the shaft was notched", and so it's set off in
paragraphs which are not quite as effective as
A list. Very commonplace in all sorts of technical writing to go step by step,
one, two, three, four, five,
and go down the list.
Again, here we have very specific details. As we'll see in a minute
it refers to particular figures, it gives variations,
it tells all the specific steps of
going through the process. You'll notice that it's in past perfect tense, "punching kit and ball peen hammer were used to stamp the
semester names of the group members" so it just went through so that someone could follow: "here's the first thing, here's the second thing,
etc, etc."
Another important concept for technical writing: Because visuals are so important
we do have to do a little bit of labor to label and explain visuals.
Again, here's the less great example:
We have an equation here. But unless you know what the equation is
because you're an expert in, because you did the experiment, then you would have no idea what this is.
There's a suggestion that this might be about measuring material removal rate,
but it doesn't say what the equation is or
where it comes from.
The following example, as you'll notice,
explicitly labels and explains what the equation is. And it also
offers an explanation and a source for the equation.
"So an equation that was helpful for the experiment was the contact pressure equation using interference values." It's very explicit
this equation can be used and this is part of the theory:
this is why we selected an equation in a particular context to do a
particular calculation and get a particular result.
Then it goes on to explain the relevant variables and give a citation, and we do have
an equation number that corresponds to the equation list in the table of contents.
You don't need to reinvent the wheel when we're thinking about visuals.
One is most readers expect that
figure labels will be underneath a picture:
"Figure 1" and then the label or caption for the figure.
The other issue is that nowhere in the text. does it talk about what this visual is.
So let's look at a better example and see what's happening here
"Figures 1 & 2 below show the mechanical drawings that were used as guidelines for machining",
It provides us with a little bit of content and context for
what the visual is, so that if we're scanning for visuals
we see it and then we can hop up to the text right before and understand exactly how this was used and why this was used.
Etc
Again, very simple: "Figure 2: Aluminum plate dimensions." Standard technical drawing.
Just a few more examples of visuals:
Notice that with graphics, with images or photographs or drawings,
the figure label and caption goes beneath the figure. With tables, data tables,
etc., the table label and
title goes above the information.
One of the other important things you can do is to read and follow your specs. If your instructor provides you with guidelines or
specifications for the assignment, it will be very useful for you to read them carefully and follow the directions.
Ask for examples of good lab reports if they have them.
Writing is a process of multiple drafts, focusing on different revisions at different steps in the process.
Don't worry, for example, about third person and personal pronouns in the first draft.
Just get the thing written. You can revise for personal pronouns or past tense issues later.
Also, it's a good habit to begin reading the technical literature with an attention to how authors get ideas across.
How do they introduce problems? How technical is their language? How direct are their sentences?
Reading like an engineer and thinking about how or why engineers read will help you to write like one, too
Finally I'd like to point you to a few resources for a variety of writing issues.
The first website, "Writing as an Engineer or Scientist" provides a variety of examples,
videos. and more content about a variety of scientific writing issues.
"Online Technical Writing" is an online open access textbook that's very useful for thinking about
not only sentence style and revision strategies, but also it has plenty of examples and content about different kinds of
technical writing genres and situations.